So welcome everyone to CS 25.
We're excited to
kick off this class.
This is the fourth iteration
of the class we're doing.
In the previous iterations,
we had like Andrej Karpathy
come last year, we also
had Geoffrey Hinton,
a bunch of other people.
And so we're very
excited to kick this off.
The purpose of this
class is to discuss
the latest in the field
of AI, and transformers,
and large language models, and
have all the top researchers
and experts in the field come
and be able to directly give
a talk and discuss
their findings
and their new ideas
to students here so
that this can be used
to in their own research
or spark new collaborations.
So we're very excited
about the class.
And yeah, let's kick it off.
So hi, everyone.
I'm Div.
So I'm currently on a leave from
the PhD program from Stanford.
I'm working on a personal AI
agent startup called MultiOn.
You can see the shirt.
I'm very passionate
about robotics, agents,
did a lot of work
on reinforcement
learning, a bunch of
state of art methods
on online and offline Rl.
Previously was working with
Ian Goodfellow at Apple.
So that was really fun.
And just really
passionate about AI,
and how can you apply
that in the real world.
It's a guy.
Hey, guys.
I'm Steven, currently a
second year a PhD student
here at Stanford.
So I'll be interning at
NVIDIA over the summer.
And previously, I was a master's
student at Carnegie Mellon,
and an undergrad
at the University
of Waterloo in Canada.
So my research interests
broadly hover around NLP
and working with
language and text.
You know, can we work on
improving the controllability
and reasoning capabilities
of language models.
And recently, I've gotten more
into multimodal work, as well as
interdisciplinary work with
psychology and cognitive
science.
I'm trying to bridge
the gap between how
humans, as well as language
models learn and reason.
And just some for fun.
You know, I'm also the
co-founder and co-president
of the Stanford Piano Club.
So if anybody here is
interested, check us out.
Hi, everyone.
I'm Emily.
I am currently an undergrad,
about to finish it
up in math and cogsci
here at Stanford,
and also doing my master's
in computer science.
I am super interested
similarly in the intersection
of artificial intelligence
and natural intelligence.
I think questions around
neuroscience, philosophy,
and psychology are
really interesting.
And I've been very lucky to do
some really cool research here
at Stanford Med at NYU
and also at CoCoLab
where Steven is working
as well under Noah Goodman
on some computational
neuroscience and computational
cognitive science work.
And currently I am beginning
a new line of research
with Chris Manning
and Chris Potts
doing some NLP
interpretability research.
Hello.
I'm a first year CS
master's student.
My name is Seonghee.
I do research around
natural language processing.
I did a lot of research in HCI
during undergrad at Cornell.
And I'm currently working
on visual language models
in image editors
for accessibility,
and I'm also working with
Professor Hari Subramonyam
in the HCI department,
and I'm also
working on establishing
consistency in long term
conversations with Professor
Diyi Yang at the NLP group.
Yeah.
Nice to meet you all.
So what we hope you guys
will learn from this course
is a broad idea of how
exactly transformers work.
How they're being applied around
the world beyond just NLP,
but other domains as
well as applications.
Some exciting new
directions of research.
Innovative techniques
and applications,
especially these days of
large language models, which
have taken the world by storm.
And any remaining
challenges or weaknesses
involving transformers and
machine learning in general.
Cool.
So we can start with presenting
first the attention timeline.
So I will say initially we used
to have this prehistoric era,
where we had very simple
methods, so language,
for example.
So like you had a lot
of rule-based methods,
you had parsing, you
have RNNs, LSTMs.
And that all
changed, I will say,
in the beginning of around
2014 when people started
studying attention mechanisms.
And this was around say
initially around images,
can you adapt the mechanism
of-- how attention
works in the human brain.
Images, can you focus
on different parts,
which might be more salient or
more relevant to a user query
or what you care about.
And I will say
attention exploded
in the beginning of 2017, with
the paper Attention Is All You
Need by Ashish Vaswani et al.
And so that was when
transformers became mainstream.
And then people realized,
OK, like this could
be its own really big thing.
It's a new architecture
that you can use everywhere.
And after that, we saw an
explosion of transformers
into NLP, with BERT, GPT-3.
And then into also other fields.
So now you're seeing
that in like vision,
like protein folding
with Alphafold.
You have all the video
models like Sora.
Everything right
now is basically
some combination of attention,
and some other architectures,
like diffusion, for example.
And this has now led to the
start of this generative AI
era, where now you have all
this powerful models, which
are billion parameters,
trillion parameters.
And then you can use this for a
lot of different applications.
And so if you think
about even like one year
before, AI was very
limited to the lab,
and now you can see AI
has escaped from the lab,
it's now finding real life--
real world applications.
And it has started to
become predominant.
If you look at the
trajectory right now,
it's sort of like we're
on this upward trend,
where we started like
this, and now it's
just growing faster,
and faster, and faster.
And every month, there's just
so many new models coming out.
It's like every day, there's
just so many new things
happening.
And so it's going to be very
exciting to see even a year
or two years from now
how everything changes.
And the society will be led
by this revolutions that are
happening in the field of AI.
So a lot of things are
going to change, and maybe
how we interact
with technology, how
we do things in daily life,
how we have assistants.
And I think a lot
of that will just
come from the things we might
be studying in this class.
Awesome.
Thanks, Div, for going
through the timeline.
So generally, the field of
natural language processing,
which is kind of
what transformers
were originally invented for.
The fundamental
discrete nature of text
makes many things difficult.
For example, data augmentation
is more difficult.
You can't just,
for example, flip,
flip it like you flip an image,
change the pixel values a bit.
It's not that simple.
Text is very precise.
One wrong word, changes the
entire meaning of a sentence,
or makes it completely
nonsensical.
And there's also potential
for long context length
as well as memories.
Like, if you're
chatting with ChatGPT
over many different
conversations,
being able to learn and
store all of that information
is a big challenge.
And some of the weaknesses
of earlier models,
which we'll get to later,
short context length,
linear reasoning,
as well as the fact
that many of the
earlier approaches
did not adapt based on context.
So actually, I'll be
running through briefly
how NLP has progressed
throughout the years.
Actually, Seonghee
will be doing that.
Yeah.
While preparing this, I found
this really interesting thing.
This is 1966.
This was the earliest
chatbot called Eliza.
And it wasn't like
a real AI, but it
was more of simulating
patterns of text and words
and sort of creating an
illusion that this chatbot was
sort of understanding
what you were saying.
So these were like the
earliest forms of NLP,
and they were mostly
rule-based approaches
where you're trying
to understand
the patterns in
sentences, patterns
and what words are said.
And these were the earliest
linguistic foundations learning
about semantic parsing.
Yeah.
Then we needed to go
on to understand more
deeper meanings within words.
So we come up with things
called Word Embeddings, which
are vector
representations of words,
and they gave us different
semantic meanings
in words that we weren't
able to understand before.
So we create vector
representations,
words that are similar
appear closer together
in this vector space,
and we're able to learn
different types of meanings.
And then these examples I have
here are word two, vec, love,
bird, Elmo.
These are different
types of word embeddings
and they sort of evolve.
So word two vector is
like a local context word
embedding, word glove, we
get like global context
within documents.
So now that we have
ways to represent words
into vector representations,
now we can turn them into--
put them into our models
and do different types
of tasks, such as
question/answering, or text
summarization, or sentence
completion, machine translation.
And we develop different
types of models
that are able to do that.
So here we have
RNNs, LSTMs that are
used for different
translation tasks.
And so since we have our
models, the now new challenge
becomes to understand how we
can do these tasks better.
So thanks, Seonghee.
So she talked about
sequence to sequence models.
Those are naturally just
inefficient as well as
ineffective for many ways.
You cannot parallelize because
it depends on recurrence.
It relies on maintaining
a hidden context
vector of all the previous
words and their information.
So you couldn't parallelize
and it was inefficient and not
very effective.
So this led to what is now
known as attention as well
as transformers.
So as the word kind
of infers, attention
means being able
to focus attention
to different parts of something.
In this case, a piece of text.
So this is done by using a set
of parameters called weights,
that basically determine
how much attention to should
be paid to each input
at each time step.
And their computer using
a combination of the input
as well as the current
hidden state of the model.
So this will become clearer
as I go through the slides.
But you're here, you
have an example--
or this is an example
of self-attention.
If we're currently
at the word "it,"
we want to know how much
attention do we want to place
to all of the other words
within our input sequence.
And again, this will become
clearer as I explain more.
So the attention
mechanism relies mainly
on these three things called
queries, keys, and values.
So I tried to come up with
a good analogy for this.
And it's basically
like a library system.
So let's say your query is
something you're looking for.
For example, a
specific topic, like I
want books about
how to cook a pizza.
And each book in the
library, let's say,
has a key that
helps identify it.
For example, this
book is about cooking.
This book is about transformers.
This book is about movie
stars, and so forth.
And what you do is you can look.
You can match between your query
as well as each of these keys
or summaries to figure
out which books give you
the most information you need.
And that information
is the value, which
you're trying to retrieve.
But here in attention,
we do a soft match.
We're not trying to
retrieve one book.
We want to see what is the
distribution of relevance
or importance across all books.
For example, this book
might be the most relevant.
I should spend
most of my time on.
This one might be the
second most relevant,
I'll spend a mediocre
amount of time on.
And then book three is less
relevant, and so forth.
So attention is
basically a soft match
between finding
what's most relevant,
which is contained
in those values.
And hence the equation,
when you multiply queries
by keys and then you
multiply that by the values
to get your final attention.
And here's also
just a visualization
from the Illustrated transformer
about how self-attention works.
So you're basically
able to embed your input
words into vectors.
And then for each of these,
you initialize a query key
as well as value matrix.
And these are learned as
the transformers strength.
And you're able to multiply your
inputs by these queries, keys,
and values to get
these final query, key,
and value matrices, which
is then used, again,
as shown in the formula to
calculate the final attention
score.
And the way the
transformer works is it
basically uses attention,
but in a way that's
called multi-head attention,
as in we do attention
several times.
Because since each one
is randomly initialized,
our goal is that each
head of attention
will learned something
useful but different
from the other heads.
So this allows you
to get a more sort
of overarching representation of
potentially relevant information
from your text.
And you see these blocks
are repeated N times.
The point there is once
the multi-head attention is
calculated, so the
attention scores
are calculated from each head,
they're then concatenated.
And then this process is
repeated several times
to potentially learn things like
hierarchical features and more
in-depth information.
And here you'll see this
transformer diagram has
both an encoder and decoder.
This is for something,
for example, T5 or BART,
which is an encoder/decoder
model used for things
like machine translation.
On the other hand, things
like GPT or ChatGPT,
that's simply a
decoder-only, because there's
no second source of
input text, compared
to something like
machine translation,
where you have a sentence
in English which you
want to translate to French.
When you're decoding for
an autoregressive left
to right language
model like ChatGPT,
it basically only has what
has been generated so far.
So that's the difference between
decoder-only and encoder/decoder
transformers.
And the way multi-head
attention works
is you initialize a different
set of queries, keys,
and values, these different
matrices per head, which are all
learned separately as you
train and back propagate across
tons of data.
So again, you embed
each word, split these
into heads, so
separate matrices,
and then you kind of
multiply those together
to get the final
resulting attention, which
are then concatenated
and multiplied
by a final weight matrix.
And then there's some linear
layer and then some softmax
to help you predict the
next token, for example.
So that's the general gist of
how multi-head attention works.
If you want a more in-depth
description of this,
there's lots of resources
online as well as other courses.
And I'll briefly touch upon,
like I said, cross-attention.
So here you have actually
an input sequence
and a different output sequence.
For example, translating
from French to English.
So here, when you're
decoding your output,
your English translated
text, there's
two sources of attention.
One is from the encoder.
So the entire encoded
hidden state of the input.
And that's called
cross-attention
because it's between two
separate pieces of text.
Your queries here are your
current decoded outputs.
And your keys and values
actually come from the encoder.
But there's a second
source of attention,
which is self-attention between
the decoded words themselves.
So they're the queries,
keys, and values are entirely
from the decoded side.
And these types of architectures
combine both types of attention.
Compared to, like I said,
a decoder-only model, which
would only have self-attention
among its own tokens.
And so how exactly are
transformers compared with RNNs?
So RNNs or recurrent
neural networks,
they had issues representing
long range dependencies.
There were issues with gradient
vanishing, as well as explosion.
Since you're concatenating
all of this information
into one single hidden vector,
this leads to a lot of issues
potentially.
There were a large number
of training steps involved,
and like I said, you
can't parallelize
because it's sequential
and relies on recurrence.
Whereas transformers can
model long range dependencies.
There's no gradient vanishing
or exploding problem.
And it can be parallelized.
For example, to take
more advantage of things
like GPU compute.
So overall, it's much
more efficient and also
much more effective at
representing language.
And hence why it's one of the
most popular deep learning
architectures today.
So large language
models are basically a
scaled up version of this
transformer architecture.
Up to millions or
billions of parameters.
And parameters
here are basically
nodes in the neural network.
They're typically trained on
massive amounts of general text
data.
For example, mining a bunch of
text from Wikipedia, Reddit,
and so forth.
Typically there are processes
to filter this text.
For example, getting rid
of Nazi for work things
and general quality filters.
And the training objective is
typically next token prediction.
So again, it's to predict the
next token, or the most probable
next token given all
of the previous tokens.
So again, this is how
the autoregressive
left to right architecture
like ChatGPT works.
And it's also been
shown that they
have emergent abilities
as they scale up,
which Emily will talk about.
However, they have heavy
computational cost.
Training these huge
networks on tons of data
takes a lot of time,
money, and GPUs.
And it's also led to the
fact that this can only
be done effectively at
big companies, which
have these resources
as well as money.
And what's happened now is we
have very general models, which
you can use and plug
and play and use them
on very on different
tasks without needing
to retrain them using things
like in-context, learning,
transfer learning,
as well as prompting.
And now Emily will
talk about emergent.
Yeah.
So I guess a natural
question for why
language models work so well, is
what happens when you scale up.
And as we've seen
in the past, there's
been this big trend of investing
more money into our compute,
making our models larger,
and larger, and larger.
And actually we have seen some
really cool things come out
of it, which we have now
termed emergent abilities.
We can call emergent
abilities, an ability
that is present in a larger
model, but not in a smaller one.
And I think the thing that is
most interesting about this
is emergent abilities
are very unpredictable.
It's not necessarily like
we have a scaling law
that we just keep training,
and training, and training
this model and we can say,
oh, at this training step,
we'll have this ability to
do this really cool thing.
It's actually something more
like, it's kind of random.
And then at this
threshold that is
pretty difficult or impossible
to predict, it just improves.
And we call that a
phase transition.
And this is a figure
taken by a paper authored
by a speaker we'll
have next week--
Jason Wei, who I'm very
excited to hear from,
and he did this really
cool research project
with a bunch of
other people, sort
of characterizing and exhibiting
a lot of the emergent abilities
that you can notice
in different models.
So here we have five
different models.
And a lot of
different common tasks
that we test language models on
to see what their abilities are.
And so, for example, complicated
arithmetic, or transliteration,
being able to tell
if someone is telling
the truth, other
things like this.
And as you can notice
on this figure,
we have these eight graphs, and
there's this very obvious spike.
It's not necessarily like this
gradual increase in accuracy.
And so that is sort of what we
can term that phase transition.
And currently there's
very few explanations
for why these abilities emerge.
Evaluation metrics used to
measure these abilities,
don't fully explain
why they emerge.
And an interesting
research paper
that came out recently by
some researchers at Stanford
actually claimed that maybe
emergent abilities of LLMs
are nonexistent.
Maybe it's more so
the researchers choice
of metric being
nonlinear rather than
fundamental changes in the
model responding to the scale.
And so a natural question is,
is scaling the best thing to do?
Is it the only thing to do?
Is it the most significant way
that we can improve our models?
And so while scaling is a factor
in these emergent abilities,
it is not the only factor,
especially in smaller models.
We have new architectures,
higher quality data,
and improved training procedures
that could potentially
bring about these emergent
abilities on smaller models.
And so these present a lot of
interesting research directions,
including improving
few-shot prompting abilities
as we've seen before
through other methods,
and theoretical and
interpretability
research, computational
linguistics work, and yeah,
other directions.
And so as some
interesting questions,
do you believe that emergent
abilities will continue
to arise with more scale?
Is there like maybe once
we get to some crazy number
of parameters, then
our language models
will suddenly be able
to think on their own
and do all sorts of cool things,
or is there some sort of limit.
What are your thoughts
on this current trend
of larger models and more data?
Is this a good direction?
Larger models obviously mean
more money, more compute,
and Less democratization
of AI research.
And thoughts on retrieval
based or retrieval
augmented systems compared
to simply learning everything
within the parameters
of the model.
So lots of cool directions.
Yeah.
So we have some quick
introductions on reinforcement
learning from human feedback.
I think a lot of you
might already know.
So reinforcement learning
from human feedback
is a technique to train
large language models.
Usually, you give
human like humans
two outputs of the
language model.
Ask them what they prefer.
We select the one they
prefer, and feed it back
into the model to train a
more human aligned model.
Recently, there has been more--
since reinforcement,
learning from human feedback
has its limitations, you
need quality human feedback,
you need good rewards,
you need a good policy.
It's very complicated
training process.
A recent paper, DPO,
uses just preference data
and non-preference data and
feeds that into the language
model to--
it's a much more
faster algorithm
to train these language models.
So quick introduction to GPT.
We have ChatGPT, which
is fine-tuned on GPT-3.5.
We have a diagram of the
different types of GPT models
that have been released.
And GPT-4 is the next
version, and it's
supervised on a large
training dataset with RLHF,
the APIs of text [? FNC ?]
also have been trained on RLHF.
Then we have Gemini,
which is Gemini,
a model, which was like
basically Google's AI from BART,
now is Gemini.
And when it was released,
there was like a big hype
because it performed
much better than ChatGPT
on like 30 out of the
32 academic benchmarks.
So there was a lot of
excitement around this.
And now as people
have used it, there
have been different
like, we realized
that different models are good
for different types of tasks.
One interesting
thing is that Gemini
is trained on the MoE model,
which is a mixture of experts
model where we have a bunch of
smaller neural networks that
are known as experts and are
trained and capable of handling
different things.
So we could have
one neural network
that's really good at pulling
images from the web, one
good at pulling like text.
And then we have our
final gated network,
which response is the best
suited to address the request.
So now that takes us to
where we are right now.
So AI, especially NLP
large language models
have taken off, like Seonghee
said, things like GPT-4, Gemini,
and so forth.
A lot of things involving human
alignment and interaction,
such as RLHF.
There's more work now on trying
to control the toxicity bias as
well as ethical
concerns involving
these models, especially
as more and more people
gain access to them,
things like ChatGPT.
There's also more use
in unique applications,
things like audio, music,
neuroscience, biology,
and so forth.
We'll have some slides
briefly touching upon those,
but these things are mainly
touched upon by our speakers.
And there's also
diffusion models.
A separate class of models,
although now there's a diffusion
transformer where they
replace the U-net backbone
in the diffusion model with the
transformer architecture, which
works better for things like
text-to-video generation.
For example, Sora uses
the diffusion transformer.
So what's next?
So as we see the use of
transformers and machine
learning get more and more
prominent throughout the world.
It's very exciting,
but also scary.
So it can enable a
lot more applications,
things like very
generalist agents,
longer video understanding
as well as generation.
Maybe in five, 10 years, we can
generate a whole Netflix series
by just putting in a prompt or
an a description of the show we
want to watch.
Things like incredibly
long sequence modeling,
which Gemini--
I think now it is
able to handle.
They claim a million
tokens for more.
So we'll see if that
can further scale up,
which is very exciting.
Things like very domain-specific
foundation models,
things like having a
DoctorGPT, LawyerGPT,
any sort of GPT for any use case
or application you might want.
And also other potential
real world impacts,
personalized education, as
well as tutoring systems,
advanced healthcare diagnostics,
environmental monitoring,
and so forth, real-time
multilingual communication.
You go to China, Japan
or something, real-time,
you're able to
interact with everyone.
As well as interactive
entertainment and gaming.
Potentially, we can
have more realistic NPCs
which are run by
transformers as well as AI.
And so what's missing?
You know, there's this
buzzword, AGI/ASI--
artificial general intelligence
or superintelligence.
So what's really
missing to get there?
These are some of
the things that we
thought might be the case.
Firstly, is reducing
computation complexity.
As these models and
datasets scale up,
it will become even more
costly and difficult to train.
So we need a way to reduce that.
And hence, human
controllability of these models,
the alignment of language
models potentially
with the human brain, adaptive
learning and generalization
across even more domains,
multisensory multimodal
embodiment.
This will allow
it to learn things
intuitive physics and common
sense that humans are able to.
But since these models,
especially language models
are trained purely on
text, they don't actually
have a sort of intuitive
or human-like understanding
of the real world, since
all they've seen is text.
Infinite or external
memory, as well as
self-improvement and
self-reflection capabilities.
Like humans, we're able to
continuously learn and improve
ourselves.
Complete autonomy and long
horizon decision-making,
emotional intelligence
and social understanding,
as well as, of course, ethical
reasoning and value alignment.
Cool.
So let's get to some of the
interesting parts about LLMs.
So there's a lot of applications
we are already starting
to see in the real world.
Like the ChatGPT is one
of the biggest examples.
It's like the fastest growing
consumer app in history,
which just went really viral.
Everyone started using it.
Just cause this people know
AI exists in the real world
and cause it.
Before that was just
segment say people us
who are at Stanford
who are using AI.
And then a lot of the
people in the world
were like, OK, what is even AI?
When they got their first
experience with ChatGPT,
they were like,
OK, like, OK, like.
This thing actually works.
We believe in that.
And now we are starting
to see a lot of this
in different applications,
like speeches or something,
where you have a lot of this
new models, like Whisper,
you also have this
ElevenLabs, bunch
of things that are happening.
Music is a big industry.
Images and videos are also
like starting to transform.
So we can imagine maybe
five years from now,
all Hollywood movies might be
produced by like video models.
You might not even need
actors, for example.
You might just have
fake actors and like,
you spend like
billions of dollars
just going to different parts in
the world and shooting scenes.
But that can all be just
done by a video model.
So something like Sora and
what's happening right now,
I think that's going to be
game-changing because that's
how movie production,
advertisement,
all of maybe social media
will be driven by that.
And it's already
fascinating to just see
how realistic all these
images and the videos look.
It's almost like better than
like a human artist quality.
So it's getting very
interesting and very hard
to also distinguish what's
real and what's fake.
And one very
interesting application
will be when you can
take these models
and embody them
in the real world.
So for example, if you have
some games like Minecraft,
for example, where you can have
an AI that can play the game,
and then we are already
starting to see that where
there's a lot of work
where you have an AI that's
masquerading as a human.
And it's actually able
to go and win the game.
So there's a lot of this stuff
that's happening in real-time
and people are doing that.
And it's actually,
we are reaching
some level of
superhuman performance
there in virtual games.
Similarly in the
robotics, it'll be
very exciting to see
once you can apply
AI in the physical
world, you can just
enable so many applications.
You can have physical helpers
in your home, industry, so on.
And there's almost a race for
building the humanoid robots
that's going on right now.
So if you look at
what Tesla is doing,
what's this company
called Figure is doing.
So everyone is really
excited about, OK,
can we go and build this
physical helpers that
can go and help you with
a lot of different things
in real life.
And so definitely a lot of
fun research and applications
have already been applied
by OpenAI, DeepMind, Meta,
and so on.
And we've also seen a lot
of interesting applications
in biology and healthcare.
So Google introduced this
Med-PaLM model last year.
We actually had the
first author of the work
give a talk in the last
iteration of the course.
This is very
interesting because this
is a transformer
model that can be
applied for actual
medical applications.
Google is right now deploying
this in actual hospitals
for analyzing, like the patient
health data, a lot of history,
medical diagnosis,
cancer detection, so on.
So now we'll touch
briefly upon some
of the recent trends in terms
of transformers research,
as well as potentially remaining
weaknesses and challenges.
So as I explained earlier, you
know, a large amount of data
compute and cost to train,
over weeks or months,
thousands of GPUs.
And now there's this thing
called the BabyLM challenge--
can we train LLMs using similar
amounts of text data baby
is exposed to while growing up?
So essentially,
comparing LLMs and humans
is one aspect of
my own research.
I believe that
children are different.
We learn very differently
as humans compared to LLMs.
They do statistical learning.
This requires a
large amount of data
to actually learn statistical
relations between words,
in order to get things like
abstraction, generalization,
and reasoning capabilities.
Whereas human's learn
in more structured,
probably smarter ways.
For example, learn in more
compositional or hierarchical
manners, which will allow us to
learn these things more easily.
And so one of my
professors, Michael Frank,
he made this tweet showing how--
this four to five orders
of magnitude difference
between human and LLM
emergence of many behaviors.
And this is magnitude, not time.
So like 10,000 up to a millions
of times as much data required
for LLMs compared to humans.
This may be to the fact that
humans have innate knowledge.
This relates to
priors basically.
You know, when we're born,
maybe due to evolution,
we already have some
fundamental capabilities
built into our brains.
Second is multimodal grounding.
We don't just learn from texts.
We learn from interacting with
the world, with other people
through vision, smell, things we
can hear, see, feel and touch.
The third is active
social learning.
We learn while
growing up by talking
to our parents,
teachers, other children.
This is not just
basic things, but even
things like values, human values
to treat others with kindness
and so forth.
And this is not
something that LLM
is really exposed to
when it's trained on just
large amounts of text data.
Kind of related is this trend
towards smaller open source
models, potentially
things we can even
run on our everyday devices.
For example, there's more
and more work on AutoGPT
as well as ChatGPT plugins.
Smaller open source models
like LLaMA, as well as
Mistral models.
And in the future,
hopefully we'll
be able to finetune and run even
more models locally, potentially
even on our smartphone.
Another area of
research and work
is in memory augmentation
as well as personalization.
So current big
weakness of LLMs is
they're sort of
frozen in knowledge
at a particular point in time.
They don't augment
knowledge on the fly
as they're talking to you.
It's not stored into their
brain, the parameters.
The next time you start
a new conversation,
there's a very high
chance it won't remember
anything you said before.
I'll get to RAG in a bit.
So one of our goals
hopefully in the future
is to have this wide scale
memory augmentation as well
as personalization.
Somehow update the
model on the fly
while talking to hundreds or
thousands or millions of users
around the world.
And to adapt not
only their knowledge,
but their talking style
as well as persona
to the particular user.
And this is called
personalization.
This could have many
different applications,
such as mental health
therapy, and so forth.
So some potential
approaches for this
could be having a memory bank.
This is not that feasible
with larger amounts of data.
Prefix-tuning approaches, which
finetunes only a very small
portion of the model.
However, when you
have such huge LLMs,
even finetuning a very
small portion of the model
is incredibly expensive.
Maybe some prompt-based
approaches in context learning.
However, again, this will
not change the model itself.
It will likely not carry forward
among different conversations.
And there's this
thing now called
RAG-- retrieval-augmented
generation, which
is related to memory
bank, where you have
a data store of information.
And each time when the user
puts in an input query,
you first look at if
there's relevant information
from this data store,
that you can then
augment as context into LLM
to help guide its output.
This relies on having a high
quality external data store.
And it's also typically
not end-to-end.
And the main thing
here is it's not
within the brain of
the model, but outside.
It's suitable for knowledge
or fact-based information.
But it's not really
suitable for enhancing
the fundamental capabilities
or skills of the model.
There's also lots of work now
on pre-training data synthesis,
especially after ChatGPT
and GPT-4 came out.
Instead of having
to collect data
from humans, which can be very
expensive and time-consuming,
many researchers now are
using GPT-4 for example,
to collect data, to
train other models.
For example, model
distillation, training
smaller and less
capable models with data
from larger models like GPT-4.
An example is the
Microsoft Phi models
introduced from their paper--
Textbooks Are All You Need.
And speaking a bit more
about the Phi model,
it's a 2.7 billion parameter
model, Phi version 2,
and it excels in
reasoning in language.
Challenging or having
comparative performance
to compare two models
up to 25 times larger,
which is incredibly impressive.
And their main takeaway here
is the quality or source
of data is incredibly important.
So they emphasize textbook
quality training data
and synthetic data.
They generated synthetic
data to teach the model
common sense reasoning
and general knowledge.
This includes things like
science, daily activities,
theory of mind, and so forth.
They then augmented this with
additional data collected
from the web that
was filtered-based
on educational value as
well as content quality.
And what this allowed them to do
is train a much smaller model,
much more efficiently,
while challenging models up
to 25 times larger, which
is, again, very impressive.
Another area of debate is
are LLMs truly learning.
Are they learning new knowledge?
When you ask it to
do something, is it
generating it from scratch?
Or is it simply regurgitating,
something it's memorized before?
This line has been blurred
and it's not clear,
because the way LLMs learn is
from, again, learning patterns
from lots of texts, which you
can say is somewhat memorizing.
There's also the potential
for test time contamination.
Models might
regurgitate information,
it's seen during training
while being evaluated,
and this can lead to
misleading benchmark results.
There's also
cognitive simulation.
So a lot of people arguing
that LLMs mimic human thought
processes, while others say no.
It's just a sophisticated
form of pattern matching,
and it's not nearly as
complex or biological
or sophisticated as a human.
And this also leads to a lot
of ethical as well as practical
limitations.
So, for example,
I'm sure you've all
heard that recent lawsuit,
copyright lawsuit by New York
Times on OpenAI, where they
claim that OpenAIs ChatGPT was
basically regurgitating existing
New York Times articles.
And this is again,
this issue with LLMs
potentially memorizing
text it saw during training
rather than synthesizing
new information entirely
from scratch.
Another big source
of challenge, which
might be able to close the
gap between current models
and eventually maybe
AGI is this concept
of continual learning,
AKA, infinite
and permanent fundamental
self-improvement.
So humans were able to
learn constantly, every day
from every interaction.
I'm learning right now
from just talking to you
and giving this lecture.
We don't need to
finetune ourselves.
We don't need to sit-in a
chair and then have someone
read the whole internet
to us every two months
or something like that.
Currently, there's
work on finetuning,
a small model based on
traces from a better model,
or the same model after
filtering those traces.
However, this is closer to
retraining and distillation
than it is to true human
continual learning.
So that's definitely, I think,
at least a very exciting
direction.
Another area of challenge is
interpreting these huge LLMs
with billions of parameters.
They're essentially
huge black-box models,
where it's really
hard to understand
exactly what is going on.
If we were able to
understand them better,
this would allow us to
know what exactly we
should try to improve.
It also allows us to
control these models better,
and potentially lead to better
alignment as well as safety.
And there's this
area of work called
mechanistic
interpretability, which
tries to understand exactly how
the individual components, as
well as operations in a
machine learning model
contribute to its overall
decision-making process.
And to try to unpack
that black-box, I guess.
So speaking a bit more
about a concept related
to mechanistic interpretability
as well as continual learning
is model editing.
So this is a newer
line of work which
hasn't seen too much
investigation, also because it's
very challenging.
But basically, this
looks like can we
edit very specific
nodes in the model
without having to retrain it.
So one of the papers
I linked there, they
developed a causal
intervention method to trace
the neural activations for
model factual predictions,
and they came up
with this method
called Rank-One Model
Editing or ROME,
that was able to modify
very specific model
weights for updating
factual associations.
For example, Ottawa is
the capital of Canada
and then modifying
that to something else.
They found they didn't need
to re-finetune the model.
They were able to
inject that information
into the model, pretty
much in a permanent way
by simply modifying
very specific nodes.
They also found that
mid-layer feedforward modules
played a very significant
role in storing
these sorts of factual
information or associations.
And the manipulation of these
can be a feasible approach
for model editing.
So I think this is
a very cool line
of work with potential
long term impacts.
And as Seonghee stated
before, another line of work
is basically mixture of experts.
So this is very prevalent
in current day LLMs,
things like GPT-4 and Gemini.
And so to have several models
or experts work together
to solve a problem, and
arrive at a final generation.
And there's a lot
of research on how
to better define and
initialize these experts
and connect them to come
up with a final result.
And I'm thinking, is
there a way of potentially
having a single model
variation of this similar
to the human brain?
For example, the human brain,
we have different parts
of our brain for
different things.
One part of our brain might work
more for spatial reasoning, one
for physical reasoning, one for
mathematical logical reasoning,
and so forth.
Maybe there's a way of
segmenting a single neural
network or model in such a way.
For example, by adding more
layers on top of a foundation
model, and then only finetuning
those specific layers
for different purposes.
Related to continual learning
is self-improvement as well as
self reflection.
So there's been a
lot of work recently
that's also shown that
models, especially LLMs, they
can reflect on their own output
to iteratively refine as well
as improve them.
It's been shown that
this improvement can
happen across several
layers of self-reflection.
Having a mini version
of continual learning
up to a certain degree.
And some folks believe
that AGI is basically
a constant state
of self-reflection,
which is, again, similar
to what a human does.
Lastly, a big issue is
the hallucination problem,
where a model does not
know what it does not know.
And due to the
sampling procedure,
there's a very high
chance, for example,
I'm sure you've also used
ChatGPT before that it sometimes
generates text, it's
very confident about,
but is simply incorrect,
like factually incorrect
and does not make any sense.
We can potentially enhance
this through different ways.
Maybe some sort of
internal-based fact verification
approach based on
confidence scores.
There's this line of work
called model calibration,
which kind of works on
that, potentially verifying
and regenerating output.
If it finds that its
output is incorrect,
maybe it can be
asked to regenerate.
And of course, there's things
like RAG-based approaches, where
you're able to retrieve from a
knowledge store, which is also
a potential solution people
have investigated for reducing
this problem of hallucination.
Lastly, Emily will touch upon
some chain of thought reasoning.
Yeah.
So chain of thought
is something I
think is really
cool because I think
it combines the cognitive
imitation and also
interpretability
lines of research.
And so chain of
thought is the idea
that all of us, unless you have
some extraordinary photographic
memory, think through
things step by step.
If I asked you to multiply a
10 digit number by a 10 digit
number, you'd probably
have to break that down
into intermediate
reasoning steps.
And so some researchers
thought, well,
what if we do the same things
with large language models
and see if forcing
them to reason
through their ideas and
their thoughts helps
them have better accuracy
and better results.
And so chain of thought
exploits the idea
that ultimately these models
have these weights that
know more about a
problem rather than just
having it prompt and regurgitate
what just to get a response.
And so an example of
chain of thought reasoning
is on the right.
So as you can see on the left,
there's standard prompting.
So I give you this
complicated question.
Let's say we're doing
this entirely new problem.
I give you the question and
I just give you the answer,
I don't tell you how to do it.
That's kind of difficult.
Versus chain of thought.
The first example that
you get, I actually
walk you through the answer.
And then the idea
is that hopefully,
since you have this framework of
how to think about a question,
you're able to produce
a more accurate output.
And so chain of thought
resulted in pretty significant
performance gains for
larger language models.
Similarly to what I
touched upon before,
this is an emergent ability.
And so we don't really
see the same performance
for smaller models.
But something that I
think is important,
as I mentioned before, is
this idea of interpretability.
Because we can see
this model's output
as their reasoning and
their final answer,
then you can kind
of see, oh, hey,
this is where they
messed up, this
is where they got
something incorrect.
And so we're able to break down
the errors of chain of thought
into these different categories
that helps us better pinpoint,
why is it doing
this incorrectly,
how can we directly
target these issues.
And so currently,
chain of thought
works really effectively for
models of approximately 100
billion parameters or more.
Obviously, very big.
And so why is that?
An initial paper found that
one step missing and semantic
understanding chain
of thought errors
are the most common
among smaller models.
So you can think
of, oh, I forgot
to do this step in
the multiplication.
Or I actually don't really
understand what multiplication
is to begin with.
And so some potential reasons is
that maybe smaller models fail
at even relatively easy
simple mapping tasks,
they seem to have inherently
weaker arithmetic abilities,
and maybe they have
logical loopholes
and don't end up coming
at a final answer.
So all your reasoning is
correct, but for some reason,
you just couldn't
get quite there.
And so an interesting
line of research
would be to improve chain of
thought for smaller models,
and similarly allow more people
to work on interesting problems.
And so how could we
potentially do that?
Well, one idea is to generalize
this chain of thought reasoning.
So it's not necessarily that
we reason in all the same ways.
Like there are multiple ways
to think through a problem
rather than breaking
it down step by step.
And so we can perhaps
generalize chain of thought
to be more flexible
in different ways.
One example is this
tree of thoughts idea.
And so tree of
thoughts is considering
multiple different
reasoning paths,
and evaluating their
choices to decide
the next course of action.
And so this is
similar to the idea
that we can look ahead
and go backwards,
similar to a lot of the model
architectures that we've seen.
And so just having
multiple options
and being able to come out
with some more accurate output
at the end.
Another idea is
Socratic questioning.
So the idea that we are
dividing and conquering
in order to have this
self-questioning,
self-reflection idea
that Steven touched upon.
So the idea is a
self-questioning module
using a large scale
language model
to propose these
subproblems related
to the original problem
that recursively backtracks
and answers the subproblem
to the original problem.
So this is similar
to that initial idea
of chain of thought, except
rather than spelling out
all the steps for you.
The language model
reflects on how
can it break down
these problems,
how can it answer these problems
and get to the final answer.
Cool.
OK, let's see.
So let's go to some of the
more interesting topics
that are starting to become
relevant, especially in 2024.
So last year, we saw a big
explosion in language models,
especially with GPT-4 that
came out almost a year ago now.
And now what's happening is
we are starting to transition
towards more AI agents.
And it's very interesting to
see what differentiates an agent
from something like a model.
So I probably talk about a
bunch of different things,
such as actions, long-term
memory, communication,
bunch of stuff.
But let's start by, why
should we go and build agents?
Think about that.
So one key hypothesis
or I will say here is--
what's going to happen is
humans will communicate
with AI using natural
language, and AI
will be operating our machines.
Thus allowing for more intuitive
and efficient operations.
So if you think about a laptop.
If you show a laptop to
someone who's maybe a kid,
or who has never used a computer
before, they'll be like, OK,
why do I have to use this box?
Why can't I just talk to it?
Why can't it be more human-like?
I can just ask you to do
things and you can just
go do my work for me.
And that seems to be the
more human-like interface
to how things should happen.
And I think that's the way the
world will transition towards,
where instead of us
clicking or typing,
we talk to an AI using
natural language how
you talk to a human, and the
AI will go and do your work.
Actually, I have a
blog on this, which
is called Software 3.0 if
you want to check that out.
But yeah, cool.
So for agents, why?
Do you want agents?
So as it turns out, a single
call to a larger foundation AI
model is usually not enough.
You can do a lot more
by building systems.
And by systems, you mean
doing more things, like model
chaining, model reflection,
other mechanisms.
And this requires a
lot of different stuff.
So you require memory, you
require large context lengths,
you also want to
do personalization,
you want to be
able to do actions,
you want to be able
to do internet access.
And then you can accomplish
a lot of these things
with this kind of agents.
Here's a diagram breaking
down the different parts
of the agents.
This is from Lillian Weng.
She's a senior
researcher at OpenAI.
So if you want to build
really powerful agents,
you need to really just think
of that as you're building this
a new kind of
computer, which has
all this different
ingredients to build.
You have to build
memory, and you
have to think about
memory from scratch.
How do you do long-term memory?
How do you do short-term memory?
How do you do planning?
How do we think
about reflection?
If something goes wrong,
how do you correct that?
How do you have
chain of thoughts?
How do you decompose a goal?
So if I say something like
book me a trip to Italy,
for example, how do you
break that down to sub goals,
for example, for the agent?
And also being able to take
all this planning and all
this stuffs into actual action.
So that becomes
really important.
And enable all of
that using tool use.
So if you have say like
calculators, or calendars,
or code interpreters, and so on.
So you want to be able to
utilize existing tools that
are out there.
This is similar to how we as
a human, use a calculator,
for example.
So we also want AI to be
able to use existing tools
and become more
efficient and powerful.
This was actually
one of the demos.
This is actually
from my company.
But this was one of the
first demonstrations
of agents in the real
world, where we actually
had it passed the online
driving test in California.
So this was actually like a live
exam we took as a demonstration.
So this was a friends
or a driving test,
which can actually
take from your home.
And so the person had their
hands up above the keyboard,
and they were being
recorded on the webcam.
There was also like
a screen recorded.
And the DMV actually
had the person installed
like a special software
in the computer to detect,
it's not a bot.
But still the agent could
actually go and complete
the exam.
So that was interesting to see.
[LAUGHS]
So we set the
record in this case
to be the first
AI to actually get
a driving permit in California.
And this is the agent actually
going and doing things.
So here the person
has their hands just
above the keyboard
for the webcam.
And the agent is
running on the laptop
and it's answering
all the questions.
So all of this is happening
autonomously in this case.
And so this was roughly
around 40 questions.
The agent maybe made like
two or three mistakes,
but was able to
successfully pass
the whole test in this case.
So this was really fun.
Let me go to the end.
Yeah.
[LAUGHS]
So yeah.
So you can imagine,
there's a lot of fun things
that can happen with agents.
This was actually
a tech attempt.
So we informed the DMV
after we took the exam.
So this was really funny.
But you can imagine, there's
so many different things
you can enable once you have
this capabilities that are
available for everyone to use.
And this becomes a
question of, why should we
build more human-like agents?
And I would say this
is very interesting
because it's almost like
saying, why should we
build humanoid robots?
Why can't we just build a
different kind of robot?
Why do you want humanoid robots?
And it's similar question
here, why do you want,
human-like agents?
And obviously, this
is very interesting
because a lot of the technology
website is built for humans.
And then we can go and
reuse that infrastructure
instead of building new things.
And so that becomes
very interesting
because you can just deploy
these agents using the existing
technology.
Second is you can imagine this
agents could become almost
like a digital extension of you.
So they can learn about you,
they can know your preferences,
they can know what you
like, what you don't like,
and be able to act
on your behalf.
They also have very less
restrictive boundaries,
so they're able to handle
say, like logins, payments,
and so on, which might be
harder with things like API
for example.
But this is easier to do if you
are doing more computer-based
control, like a human.
You can imagine the problem
is also fundamentally simpler,
because you just have an action
space like clicking and typing,
which itself is a fundamentally
limited action space.
So that's a simpler
problem to solve
rather than building
something that
is maybe more general purpose.
And another interesting
thing about this kind
of human-like agents is
you can also teach them.
So you can teach them
how you will do things,
they can maybe
record you passively.
And they can learn from
you and then improve.
And this is also becomes
an interesting way
to improve this
agents over time.
So when we talk
about agents, there's
this map that
people like to use,
which is called the 5
different levels of autonomy.
This actually came
from self-driving cars.
So how this works is
you have L0 to L5.
So L0 to L2 is the
parts of autonomy
where the human is in control.
So here is the human
is driving the car.
And there might be some partial
automation that's happening,
which could be some
auto assist features.
This starts becoming interesting
when you have something L3.
So in L3, you still
have a human in the car,
but most of the time, the car is
able to drive itself on highways
or most of the roads.
L4 is you still have
a human, but the car
is doing all the driving.
And this is maybe if you have
driven a Tesla on autopilot
before, that's like an
L4 autonomous vehicle.
And L5 is basically you don't
have a driver in the car.
So the car is able to go and
handle all parts of the system,
there's no fallback.
And this is what like
Waymo is doing right now.
So if you take a self-driving,
if you sit-in a Waymo in SF,
then you can experience
a L5 autonomy
car, where there's
no human and the AI
is driving the whole car itself.
And so same thing also
applies for agents.
So you can almost imagine if
you are building something
like an L4 level
capability, that's
where a human is
still in the loop
and showing that
nothing is going wrong.
And so this is you still
have some bottlenecks.
But if you are able to reach
L5 level of autonomy on agents.
And that's basically saying
if you ask an agent to book
a flight and that happens.
You ask it for maybe like,
go, maybe order this for me.
Or maybe go whatever
things you care about.
And that can all
happen autonomously.
So that's where things start
to become very interesting when
we can start reaching
from L4 to L5
and don't even need a
human in the loop anymore.
Cool.
So when you think
about building agents,
this predominantly two routes.
So the first one is API, where
you can go and control anything
based on APIs that are
available out there.
So OpenAI has been trying
this with ChatGPT Plugins,
for example.
There's also a bunch
of work from Berkeley.
So Berkeley had this
work called Gorilla,
where you could train a
foundation model to control
10,000 APIs.
And there's a lot of interesting
stuff happening here.
A second direction of work is
more like direct interaction
with the computer.
And there's different
companies trying this out.
So we have one of that.
There's also this
startup called Adept
which is trying this
human-like interaction.
Yeah, maybe I can
show this thing.
So this is an idea of what you
can enable by having agents.
So what we are doing here is--
here we have our
agent and we told
it to go to Twitter
and make a post.
And so it's going and
controlling the computer
during this whole interaction.
And once it's done, it can
send me a response back,
which you can see here.
And so this becomes interesting
because you don't really
need APIs if you have
this kind of agents.
So if I have an agent that
can go control my computer,
can go control websites,
can do whatever
it wants, almost in a human-like
manner, like what you can do,
then you don't really
need APIs because this
becomes like the abstraction
layer to allow any control.
So it's going to be
really fascinating
once we have this kind of agent
start to work in the real world,
and a lot of transitions
we'll see in technology.
Cool.
OK, so let's move on to the next
topic when it comes to agents.
So one very interesting
thing here is memory.
So, yeah, so we'll say a good
way to think about a model
is almost think of it
like a compute chip.
So what happens is you have
some sort of input tokens, which
are defined in natural language,
which are going as the input
to a model.
And then you get some
output tokens out.
And the output tokens are,
again, natural language.
And if you have
something like a GPT-3.5,
that used to be something
like a 8,000 length token.
With GPT-4, this became like a
16,000 [INAUDIBLE],, one 28,000.
So you can almost imagine
this as the token size
or the instruction size of
this compute unit, which
is powered by a neural
network in this case.
And so this is basically what
GPT-4, you can imagine it.
It's almost like a CPU and
it's taking some input tokens,
defined a natural
language, doing
some computation over them,
transforming those tokens
and giving out
some output tokens.
This is actually similar to how
you think about memory chips,
for example.
So here I'm showing
a MIPS32 processor.
That's one of the earliest
processors out there.
And so what it's doing is you
have input tokens and output
tokens in binary,
like 0s and 1s.
But [INAUDIBLE] of
that, you can imagine
we are doing very
similar things,
but just over
natural language now.
And now, if you think
more about this analogy.
So you can start
thinking, OK, what
we want to do is
take whatever we have
been doing in building
computers, and CPUs, and logic,
and so on.
But can we generalize all
of that to natural language?
So you can start thinking about,
how current processors work?
How current computer chips work?
You have instructions, you have
memory, you have variables.
And then you run this
over and over to each line
of binary sequence of
instructions to output code.
And you can start thinking about
transformers in a similar way,
where you can have
the transformer acting
as a compute unit,
you are passing
it some sort of
instructions line by line.
And each instruction can
contain some primitives
which are defining
like what to do,
which could be the user command.
It could have some
memory parts, which
are retrieved from external,
like a disk, which in this case
could be like something like
a personalization system
and so on, as well as
some sort of variables.
And then you're taking this
and running this line by line.
And that's a pretty good way
to think about what something
like this could be doing.
And you can almost imagine
there could be new programming
languages you can build, which
are specific to programming
like transformers.
And so when it comes to
memory, traditionally,
how we think about
memory is like a disk.
So it's like long-lived,
it's persistent.
When the computer shuts
down, you save all your data
from the RAM to the disk,
and then you can persist it
and then you can load
it back when you want.
You want to enable something
very similar when you have AI
and you have agents.
And so you want
to have mechanisms
where I can store this data,
and then retrieve this data.
And right now how we're doing
this is like through embeddings.
So you can take any PDF or
any modality you care about,
convert that to embeddings
using an embedding model.
And store that embedding
in a vector database.
And later when we actually care
about doing any sort of access
to the memory, you can load the
relevant part of the embedding,
put that in as part
of your instruction
and feed that to the model.
And so this is how we
are thinking about memory
with AI, this space.
And then you essentially
have the retrieval models,
which are acting as a function
to store and retrieve memory.
And the embeddings becomes
the layer of the-- it's
basically the format
you're using to encode
the memory in this case.
There's still a lot
of open questions
because how this works right
now is you just do simple k-NN.
So it's very simple nearest
neighbor search, which
is not efficient, it
doesn't really generalize,
doesn't scale.
And so there's a
lot of things you
can think about, especially
hierarchy, temporal coherence.
Because a lot of memory
data is like a time series.
So there's a lot
of temporal parts.
There's also a lot of structure,
usually in a lot of data.
You could use a structure,
it could be like a graph,
for example.
And there's also a lot of things
you can do on online adaptation.
Because like most
[? chair data ?] is not static.
You're always learning,
you're always adapting,
there's things
changing all the time.
And a good model over here is
maybe how the human brain works.
So if you think about
something like the hippocampus,
it's like people still don't
know how it fully works,
but it's something you're
learning new things on the fly,
you're creating new memories,
you're adapting new memories,
and so on.
And so I think it'll be
very fascinating to see
how this area of research
evolves over time.
Similarly, like a very
relevant problem with memory
is personalization.
Suppose now you have this agents
that are doing things for you.
Then you want to make sure that
the agent actually knows what
you like, What you don't like.
Suppose you tell an agent to
go book your $1,000 flight,
but maybe it books you the wrong
flight and just wastes a lot
of your money.
Or maybe it does a lot of wrong
actions, which is not good.
So you want the agent
to learn about what
you like and understand that.
And this becomes about
forming a long-lived user
memory, for example, where
the more you interact with it,
the more it should
form a memory about you
and be able to use that.
This could have
different flavors.
So one could be like explicit
where you can tell it like,
OK, here's my allergies,
here's my flight preferences,
I like window
versus aisle seats,
here's my favorite
dishes, and so on.
But this could also be
implicit, where it could be say,
maybe I like Adidas over Nike.
Or if I'm on Amazon and if I
have this 10 different shirts I
can buy, maybe I will
buy this particular type
of shirt and brand and so on.
And so there's also a lot of
implicit learning you can do,
which is more based on
feedback or comparisons.
And there's a lot of
challenges involved here.
So you can imagine, it's how
do you collect this data?
How do you form this memory?
How do you learn?
And do you use supervised
learning versus feedback?
How do you learn on the fly?
And while you are
doing all of this, how
do you preserve user privacy?
Because like for some,
a system to personalize.
It just needs to
know a lot about you.
But then how do you
ensure that if you're
building systems like that,
that this is actually safe?
And it's not violating
any of your privacy.
An interesting area
when it comes to agents
is also communication.
So now you can imagine, suppose
you have this one agent that
can go and do things for you.
But why not have
multiple agents?
If I have an agent
and you have an agent.
And this agent starts
communicating with each other.
And so I think we'll start
seeing this phenomena
where you will have multi-agent
autonomous systems, where
each agent can go and
do things, and then
that agent can go and talk
to other agents and so on.
And so that's going
to be fascinating.
Why do you want to do this?
So one is if you have a single
agent, it will always be slow.
It has to do everything
sequentially.
But if you have a
multi-agent system,
then you can
paralyze the system.
So instead of one agent,
I had thousands of agents.
Agent can go do something
for me in parallel
instead of just having one.
Second is you can also
have spatialized agents.
So I could have an agent that's
specifically for spreadsheets,
or I have an agent that
can operate my Slack,
I have an agent that can
operate my web browser.
And then I can route
to different agents
to different things
I want to do.
And that can help.
Like this is almost what
you do in a factory.
You have spatialized
workers, each worker
is doing something
they're specialized to.
And this actually is
something that we found over
like the period
of human history,
that this is the right way
to divide tasks and get
the maximum performance.
There's a lot of
challenges here, too.
The biggest one is just how
do you exchange information.
Because now what's
happening is like everything
is happening over
natural language.
And natural language
itself is lossy.
So it's very easy to have
miscommunication gaps.
Like even when humans
talk to each other,
there's a lot of
miscommunication.
You lose information a lot,
because natural language
is ambiguous.
So you just need to have better
protocols or a better ways
to ensure that if agents are
communicating with other agents,
it doesn't cause mistakes,
it doesn't lead to a havoc,
for example.
This can also lead to
building different interesting
primitives.
So here's one example primitive
you can think about is like,
suppose what if I
have a manager agent?
And the manager agent
can go and coordinate
a bunch of worker agents.
And this is very similar to a
human organization, for example.
So you can have this hierarchy
where like, OK, if I'm a user,
I'm talking to this one main
agent, but behind the scene,
this agent is going and talking
to its own worker agents
and showing that each worker
goes and does the task.
And once everything
is done, then
the manager agent comes
back to me and says,
OK, this thing is done.
And so you can
imagine, there's a lot
of this primitives
that can be built.
A good way to also think
about this is almost
like a single-core machine
versus a multi-core machine.
So when you have a
single agent, it's
almost like saying I have
a single processor that's
powering my computer.
But now if I have
multiple agents,
I have this maybe a
16-core or 64-core machine,
where a lot of these things can
be routed to different agents,
paralyzed.
And I think that that's a
very interesting analogy when
it comes to a lot of
this multi-agent systems.
There's still a lot of
work that needs to be done.
The biggest one is just
communication is really hard.
So you need robust
communication protocols
to minimize miscommunication.
You might also just need
really good schemas.
And maybe almost how
you have HTTP that's
used to transporting
information over the internet.
You might need something
similar to transport information
between different agents.
You can also think about
some primitives here.
I will just walk through a
small example if we have time.
Suppose this is a manager agent
that wants to get tasks done,
so it gives a plan and a
context to a worker agent.
The worker can say like,
OK, I did this task.
And then we get a response back.
Then usually you want
to actually verify
if this got done or not.
Because it's possible maybe
the worker was lying to you,
for example, maybe it
failed to do the task
or something went wrong.
And so you want to actually go
and verify that this actually
was done properly.
And if everything was done,
then OK, this is good.
You can tell the user this
task was actually finished.
But what could happen is
maybe the worker actually
didn't do the task properly.
Something went wrong.
And in that case, you want to
actually go and redo the task.
And you just have to build this
sort of a failover mechanisms.
Because otherwise, there's a
lot of things that can go wrong.
And so thinking about
this syncing primitives
and how can you
ensure reliability,
how can you ensure fallback.
I think that becomes very
interesting with this kind
of agent systems.
And there's a lot of future
directions to be explored.
There's a lot of issues with
autonomous agents still.
The biggest ones are
around reliability.
So this happens because models
are stochastic in nature.
Like if our AI model,
it's stochastic.
It's a probabilistic function.
It's not fully deterministic.
And what happens is like,
if I wanted to do something,
it's possible that with
some error rate [INAUDIBLE],,
it will do something that
I didn't expect it to do.
And so like it becomes
really hard to trust it.
Because if I have traditional
code, I write a script
and I run the script through
a bunch of test cases and unit
tests.
I know, OK, if this works,
it's going to 100% of the time.
I can deploy this to millions
or billions of people.
But if our agent, it's
a stochastic function.
Maybe if it works, maybe it
works like 95% of the time.
But 5% of the time,
it still fails.
And there's no way to
fix this right now.
So that becomes
very interesting,
like, how do you actually
solve this problems?
Similarly, you see a lot of
problems around looping and plan
divergence.
So what happens here is you need
a lot of multi-turn interactions
when it comes to agents.
So you want to have the
agent do something, then
use that to do another
thing, and so on.
So take maybe hundreds
or thousands of steps.
But if it fails in
maybe the 20th step,
then it might just go haywire.
I don't know what to do
for the remaining thousands
steps of its trajectory.
And so how do you correct
it, bring it back on course?
I think that becomes
an interesting problem.
Similarly, how do you test
and benchmark these agents,
especially if they're going to
be running in the real world?
And how do you build
a lot of observability
around the systems?
If I have this agent
that's maybe has access
to my bank account, is
doing things for me,
how do I actually know
it's doing safe things?
Someone it's not
hacking into it?
How do I build trust?
And also how do we
build human fallbacks?
Like you probably want something
a 2FA if it's going to go and do
purchases for you.
Or you want like some ways to
guarantee like, OK, you just
didn't wake up and didn't have
a $0 bank account or something.
And so these are
some of the problems
that we need to solve
for agents for them
to become like real
world deployable.
And this is an example
of plan divergence
problem you see with agents.
Like, if you ask the
agent to go do something,
you will usually
expect it to follow
a path, where it will follow
some ideal path to reach
the goal.
But what might happen is
like it might actually
deviate from the path.
And once it deviates, it
doesn't know what to do.
It just keeps making
mistakes after mistakes.
And this is something
actually you
observe with early agents,
like AutoGPT, for example.
So I'm not sure if
anyone in this room
has played with AutoGPT.
Has anyone did that?
OK.
And so AutoGPT, it's
a very good prototype,
but it doesn't
actually do anything.
Because it just keeps
making a lot of mistakes,
it keeps looping around,
keeps going haywire.
And that's show's
like, OK, you really
need to have a really good ways
to correcting agents, making
sure if it makes a mistake, it
can actually come back and not
just go do random things.
So building on this, there's
also a very good analogy
from Andrej Karpathy.
So he likes to call this
the LLM operating system.
I was talking about thing
about LLMs and the agents
as building computer
chips and computers.
So you can actually start
thinking of it like that.
Here the computer
chip is the LLM
and the RAM is the context
length of the tokens
that you're feeding
into the model.
Then you have this
file system, which
is a disk, where you are
storing your embeddings.
You're able to retrieve
this embeddings.
You might have traditional
software, 1.0 tools,
which are like your calculator,
your Python interpreter,
terminal, et cetera.
You actually have this.
If you have an
operating system course,
there's this thing
called an ALU, which
is an arithmetic
logical unit, which
powers a lot of how you do
multiplications, division, so
on.
So it's very similar to that.
You just need tools to be
able to do complex operations.
And then you might also
have peripheral devices.
So you might have
different modalities,
so you might have audio,
you might have video.
You probably want to be able
to connect to the internet,
so you want to have some sort
of browsing capabilities.
And you might also want to be
able to talk to other LLMs.
And so this kind
of becomes how you
will think about a new
generation of computers
being designed with all
the innovations in AI.
Cool.
And so I'd like to end here
by saying how I imagine this
to look like in the future.
You can think of this as a
neural computer, where there's
a user that's talking to a chat
interface, behind the scene,
the chat interface
has an action engine
that can take the task route
it to different agents,
and do the task for you, and
send you the results back.
Cool.
Yeah, so to end this, a
lot of stuff that still
needs to be done for agents.
And the biggest prevalent
issues right now, I will say
is error correction.
So like, what happens
if something goes wrong?
How do you prevent the
errors from activating
in the real world?
How do you build security?
How do you build
user permissions?
What if someone tries to hijack
your computer or your agent?
How do you build robust
like a security primitives?
And also, how do you
sandbox these agents?
How do you deploy them
in risky scenarios?
So if you want to
deploy this in finance
scenarios or legal scenarios.
There's a lot of things
where you just want this
to be very stable and safe.
And that's like still something
that has not been figured out.
And there's a lot of exciting
room to think on these problems,
both on the research side
as well as application side.
Cool.
All right.
So thanks, guys, for coming to
our first lecture this quarter.
Stay back if you
have any questions.
And we might try to
get a group photo,
so if you want to be in
that, also stay back.
So next week, we're going to
have my friend, Jason Wei,
as well as his colleague,
Kyung [? Hwan ?] from OpenAI,
come give a talk.
And they're doing very
cutting edge research
involving things like large
language models at OpenAI.
And he was actually
the first author
of several of the
works we talked
about today, like
chain-of-thought reasoning,
and emergent behaviors.
So if you're in route,
please come in person.
They'll be in person.
So you'll be able to
interact with them in person.
And if you're still not
enrolled in the course
and wish to do so,
please do so on Axess.
And for the folks on
zoom, feel free to audit.
Lectures will be the same
time each week on Thursday.
And we'll announce
any notifications
by email, Canvas,
as well as Discord.
So keep your eye out for those.
And yeah, so thank you, guys.